Today's דף *Daf* is ס' *Samech*, but we pick up with the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* on נ"ט עמוד ב' *Nun Tet Amud Bet*, and
we are looking at the different ways in which מנחות minchot *Menachot*
are made or the different types of מנחות menachos *Menachot* I should
say. And the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* on נ"ט עמוד א' *Nun Tet
Amud Aleph* listed that there are some מנחות menachos *Menachot* that get
oil and לבונה levonah *Levonah*, frankincense; some get one or the other,
and some get neither. Those that get neither
specifically is the מנחת חוטא minchat chotei *Minchat Chotei* for the sin,
when, you know, based on when it's a variation of a קרבן
Korban עולה ויורד *Korban Oleh V'Yored*, a certain type of a קרבן
korban *Korban* that has a that the what you bring varies based
on the person's
economic ability, and for the סוטה Sotah, *Sotah*. Now in both of
those cases the Torah says לא ישים Lo yasim, עליה Aleha, שמן
shemen, ולא יתן yiten עליה Aleha, לבונה levonah *Lo yaseem aleha shemen
v'lo yiten aleha levonah*. You cannot put on either oil or לבונה
levonah. *Levonah*, and that actually is a negative prohibition. So this משנה
Mishna *Mishnah* deals with the negative prohibition of putting oil and לבונה
levonah *Levonah* on specifically the מנחת חוטא minchat chotei, *Minchat Chotei* and
the מנחה minchah *Mincha* for a סוטה Sotah *Sotah*, the מנחת קנאות
*Minchat Kenaot*. So let's take a look. So here we go. All
right. וחייב על השמן בפני עצמו וחייב על הלבונה בפני עצמה *V'chayav
al hashemen bifnei atzmo, v'chayav al halevonah bifnei atzmah*. So on the
משנה mishnah *Mishnah*, you transgress for the oil alone and for the
לבונה levonah *Levonah* alone even if you only do one, you transgress.
ונתן עליה aleha שמן Shemen, פסלה
*V'natan aleha shemen psalah*. If you put on an oil, you've invalidated
it. So not only have you transgressed, but you've invalidated, you can't
use the מנחה minchah *Mincha* anymore. לבונה levonah *Levonah*, if you put
on the לבונה Levonah *Levonah*, then there's a way to fix it.
ילקטנה yalk'tenah *Yilktenah*. Then just pick off the לבונה Levonah *Levonah* because
לבונה Levonah *Levonah* is more like a solid. Yeah, but not only
is it solid but not like salt, it's more like, you know,
like like rock candy. Right, like crystals, right, like we discussed before.
So somebody looked it up on the web. So anyway, so that's
easier to just pick off, okay, right? So it's not just that
it's solid, it's also like it really is like like these rock-like
things, okay, or pebble-like things. Okay, so pick it up and then
it's still כשר kasher. *Kosher*, which is interesting. So you transgress even
though you can fix it. נתן שמן shemen על שיריה אינו עובר
בלא תעשה *Natan shemen al shi'areha eino over b'lo ta'aseh*. Although we
have learned that if you make the remnant of a מנחה minchah
*Mincha* חמץ *Chametz* you transgress, לא תאפה חמץ חלקם *Lo te'afeh chametz
chelkan*, if you put oil on the remnant of a מנחה minchah.
*Mincha* you do not transgress. What, minayin... what?
Does that
not include
the בר בי רב *Bar-bi-rav*? I don't I don't know. Now, but
it's just contrasting it to the חמץ *Chametz*, okay? So if you
read a מנחה minchah. *Mincha* becomes חמץ *Chametz* after it's offered up
you transgress, if you put oil afterwards you do not. נתן כלי
k'li. על גבי כלי k'li, לא פסלה *Natan kli agabbai kli lo
psalah*. And even though we said the oil invalidates, it you know,
what does it mean to be נתן ישים עליה שמן shemen? *Natan
yaseem aleha shemen*? Let's say you had a vessel of oil, a
little bowl of oil, and you set it on top of your
מנחה minchah *Mincha*. So then you would not invalidate, you'd just remove
it, presumably you also wouldn't transgress, that's not what we mean when
we say לא ישים עליה שמן shemen, *Lo yaseem aleha shemen*, we
don't mean put it in a vessel on top of it, okay,
and that would not be a problem. So let's take a look.
Yeah, do we say that, you know, things like let's say that
you can fix, that's I'm blanking on the phrase. Right. That you're
not over on? In other words, you know, is it לאו הניתק
לעשה *Lav hanitak l'aseh* or something like that, you know, then or
I don't know if that's the right one. In other words, if
you can take the לבונה Levonah, *Levonah* off why would it be
you know what I'm saying, is it like one of these things
where
Right, well there's no עשה *Aseh*. It is true, it's reversible, but
there are things that are reversible you still transgress. You can turn
the lights on on שבת *Shabbat* and turn them back off and
you still transgress, right? No, no, but turning it off is also
an איסור Issur, *Issur*. Even if it weren't, you would still have
transgressed. I I understand, but you need there to be a specific
מצות עשה *Mitzvat Aseh* to be call it a לאו הניתק לעשה
*Lav hanitak l'aseh*. It doesn't matter that physically it's reversible. Okay, so
let's take a look.
Gift to the כהן kohen *Kohen* or to the person the donor
of the מנחה minchah, *Mincha*?
The whoever does it. I mean, it's true, it could be done
could be done by the כהן kohen *Kohen* or by the person.
But they're not able to go to the מזבח mizbeach *Mizbeach*?
No, but you could put the שמן *Shemen* or the לבונה Levonah
*Levonah* on for beforehand. Now it would have to already as we
saw before by חמץ *Chametz* already have the נתקדש בכלי *Nitkadesh b'kli*.
So right, because if it's not נתקדש בכלי *Nitkadesh b'kli* what makes
this a מנחה Mincha, *Mincha* to say that I've transgressed? Okay, so
but some of the מנחות menachos, *Minchas*, I mean we have not
yet sort of done the step-by-step process about when it's put in
the כלי k'li *Kli*, but some of it like we see that
קידוש כלי *Kidush kli* happens when you add the oil and that
can happen actually before it gets to the כהן kohen, *Kohen*. The
כהן kohen *Kohen* only starts by the קמיצה kmitzoh *Kmitzah*, מקמיצה ואילך
מצות כהונה *M'kmitzah va'eilach mitzvat kehunah*. So you're right, in theory the
owner could transgress as well. Okay, so let's take a look. תנו
רבנן Rabbanan *Tana Rabbanan*, לא ישים עליה שמן *Lo yaseem aleha shemen*,
do not put on them I think it's עליה *Aleha*, that vav
looks like an עליהם *Alehem*, I think it's might be anyway, whatever,
okay, לא ישים עליה שמן *Lo yaseem aleha shemen*, ואם שם פסל
*V'im sam pasal*. And if you put it on, you've invalidated. יכול
לא יתן עליה לבונה Levonah ואם נתן פסל v'im natan pasal, *Yakol
lo yiten aleha levonah v'im natan pasal*? Maybe the same is true
with the לבונה Levonah *Levonah*? תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar* כי חטאת chatas.
*Ki chata't* because it is a חטאת chatas, *Chatat*, this is again
by the מנחת חוטא minchat chotei. *Minchat Chotei*. יכול *Yakol*, so what
does that mean? כי חטאת *Ki chata't*, it's still a חטאת *Chatat*
even if you did it, it still retains its status. Now of
course it doesn't tell you which it's true for, for the שמן
*Shemen* or לבונה Levonah *Levonah*, but we're using our logic based on
the physical
reality. Right, to say that by the לבונה Levonah. *Levonah* it's different
because can be removed. יכול אף בשמן maybe even the oil it
retains its status? תלמוד לומר היא. talmud lomar hi. No, it only
has to be only if it's done exactly this way.
ומה ראית וסברת u'mah raita u'savarta what made you say that by
the adding the oil it's invalid but the adding of the לבונה
Levonah, you can fix it and it remains
valid? פוסלני בשמן posleni beshemen I invalidate the oil because it's impossible
to remove it, to gather it up, it got absorbed.
ומכשירני בלבונה u'machshirni balevonah it's possible to pick it up and to
remove it.
You could see it's like on the top layer, you can just
get on top.
Okay, but by the oil? Yeah, but then it's no longer the
original. Yeah, but then it's already I presume. First of all that
would be a very special circumstance and secondly how would you know
it remained on the top layer? And anyway once it's,
anyway it's already obviously into the מנחה Mincha itself so the מנחה
Mincha has to be transformed so it's clear that it
should be פסול, posul, it's that
which has inserted itself into the מנחה mincha which has changed the
nature of the מנחה. mincha Okay. בעי רב פפא בר רב הונא
מדרבי יוחנן. Ba'i Rav Papa bar Rav Huna m'de'Rabbi Yochanan. So Rav
Papa bar Rav Huna asked Rabbi Yochanan: נתן לה לבונה שחוקה מהו?
natan lah levonah sh'chuka mahu? Okay, what let's say you took this
לבונה Levonah which were like these, like they said, like crystals, and
you ground them, like you took rock crystals and you made it
into like table salt, like salt crystals made into table salt. So
now it's going to embed itself in the surface of the מנחה.
mincha Now remember, this מנחה mincha has no oil, it's basically just
flour, okay? That's what a מנחת חוטא minchat chotei, is, flour, no
שמן, no לבונה. Levonah, Okay, so you go ahead and you put
it in, it's going to embed itself within the flour, you're not
going to be able to sift it through and get it out.
Is that going to, would that also become invalid, or do we
say because it's just sitting side by side of each kernel, it
has not really
inserted itself into the kernels themselves, it's mixed with the kernels but
it has not like infused itself into the מנחה, mincha maybe that's
not enough to invalidate.
What do you do with the flour? You bake it? What's going
to happen to it?
Yeah, the question is, do you add water to it? Is it
just flour because we've already, right,
you literally could add water to
it, right, because the גמרא Gemara talked about that you can't do
קמיצה kmitzoh by נמצה כפותי nimtza k'poti and through the debate whether
you could add water? I think so. What do you do with
the flour? You put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach. and the כהן
kohen's eats the rest. You mean after the קמיצה kmitzoh it's plain?
No, but once it's offered they can do whatever they want. And
as Michael correctly reminds us, the גמרא Gemara before had a debate
about whether you're allowed to add water to it even before you
do the קמיצה kmitzoh. to make it easier to do the
קמיצה. kmitzoh? So but right, but afterwards you just
have a pile of
flour, exactly, maybe with water, maybe it's some dough.
Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara wants to know whether now of
course the interesting question here is, even if it wouldn't invalidate, you
know, because you understand the logic, I mean this is actually something
that we deal with
in תערובות ta'arovot all the time, which is there's two basic definitions
of mixtures of food. One is called לח בלח lach b'lach where
the thing is really like infused and mixed up, like in, I
don't know, some blood falls into your chicken soup, to take an
extreme example. And then there's יבש ביבש, yavesh b'yavesh, things are side
by side and you don't know which is which, like you have
one treif piece of meat mixed up with five kosher pieces of
meat. Then there are cases which are somewhere in the middle like
you have let's say, you know, non-kosher flour that was טבל tevel
let's say, mixed up with your kosher flour, but they're all mixed
up. So if you looked at each kernel, it's יבש ביבש, yavesh
b'yavesh, right, because one thing is just next to another. But obviously
from an more experiential point of view it's like לח בלח, lach
b'lach, it's all mixed up together, it's all one big unit. So
anyway, in some degree that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying here.
It's saying it's not as bad as oil in this case. It's
not like it's really infused into it, it's really sitting next to
it, but it's sitting next to it in a way that you
can't really extract it. So to what degree does that change the
definition? Now even if it doesn't change the definition and invalidate, the
funny thing is is that how you supposed to exactly do a
קמיצה? kmitzoh Right, if you did a קמיצה kmitzoh it would be
קמיצה חסירה, kmitzoh chaseirah, right, because a קמיצה kmitzoh. would not be
all flour, it would be flour with with, you know, with לבונה
Levonah, in it. So why, so it should be impossible to bring
it anyway because you can't do the קמיצה. Kemitza? For some reason
the גמרא Gemara is ignoring that question and wants to know maybe
because it's not infused into it, maybe it does not invalidate. So
let's see what the answer is. Okay, so בעי מיניה רב פפא
בר רב הונא מדרבי יוחנן. Ba'i minei Rav Papa bar Rav Huna
m'de'Rabbi Yochanan. נתן לה לבונה שחוקה natan lah levonah sh'chuka if it's
ground up מהו mahu what's the הלכה? halacha? משום דאפשר ללקטה והא
לא אפשר ללקטה mishum d'efshar leloktah v'ha lo efshar leloktah is the
reason we said it was kosher because what the ברייתא braita said
explicitly, because it could be gathered up and this can't be gathered
up, it's all this לבונה Levonah mixed with flour? או דלמא o
dilma or do we say, משום דלא מבלע mishum d'lo mivla because
it's not absorbed? והא נמי לא מבלע v'ha nami lo mivla and
this isn't absorbed? Although it said you can pick it up, but
you know, that was just describing that reality. But really it would
be sufficient that it's not absorbed, and since it's not absorbed, it
does not change its identity. Which is the story? So it says
תא שמע ta shema come and hear. דלבונה ילקטנה d'levonah yalk'tenah our
משנה Mishna. says if it's the לבונה Levonah, you fix it by
picking it off. So you see it's because it can be picked
off. So דלמא חדא ועוד קאמר dilma chada v'od ka'amar maybe it's
saying one and more than that. Meaning חדא דלא מבלע chada d'lo
mivla first of all it's not even absorbed. ועוד v'od and this
in a normal case is even better, ילקטנה you can even pick
it off. off, meaning yes it's true all these texts talk about
picking off, but that's because they could say that. Is it necessary
to have the ability to pick it off or maybe it's sufficient
that it's not absorbed, that it would still be kosher? So that's
so, so now we're gonna try again.
תא שמע, Ta Shma, come and hear: מכשירני בלבונה, Machshireni BeLevonah, the
ברייתא. Braita. I will say that the לבונה Levonah. is kosher if
it's put on this מנחה, mincha? שאפשר ללקטה, She'efshar Lelaktah, because it's
possible to pick it off. So again you see it talks about
picking it off. So הכה נמי חדא ועוד כמה, Hacha Nami Chada
Ve'od Kama, they're also saying like more than is necessary. So but
I don't know, I know these ברייתות Braitos talk about picking off,
but I don't know if that's technically what is required. So the
גמרא Gemara says מאי הוי עלה, Mai Hava Alah, what was the
upshot of this? So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman
Bar Yitzchak, תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Braita. מנחת חוטא
ומנחת קנאות, Minchat Chote U'minchat Kenaot, the מנחה mincha? of a sin
and the מנחה mincha. for jealousy for the סוטה, Sotah שנתן עליה
לבונה, Shenatan Aleha Levonah, if you put לבונה Levonah on it, מלקט
את הלבונה וכשרה, Melaket Et HaLevonah U'kesherah, you pick off לבונה Levonah?
and it becomes kosher. ואם עד שלא ליקט לבונתה, Ve'im Ad Shelo
Likat Levontah, if before you picked off the לבונה, Levonah, חישב עליה,
Chishav Aleha, you had a מחשבה, Machshava, which was, what was your
מחשבה? Machshava? Again our friend פיגול. Pigul. חוץ לזמנו או חוץ למקומו,
Chutz Lizmano O Chutz Limkomo,
whether it was a פיגול Pigul thought, to eat at the wrong
time, or a normal invalidating non-פיגול Pigul thought, to eat in the
wrong place, פסול ואין בו כרת. Pasul Ve'ein Bo Karet. It is
פסול, Pasul, there's no כרת. Karet. It doesn't become פיגול. Pigul. Why
doesn't it become פיגול Pigul if it still has לבונה Levonah. on
it? Because while it still has לבונה Levonah on it, although you
can fix it, it still is not at this moment it's not
kosher. So therefore your thought does not make it פיגול. Pigul. Now
the question is to what, why is it saying it's פסול Pasul
though? So either it's פסול Pasul because like תוספות Tosafot says, forget
your thought, it's פסול Pasul because it's got the לבונה Levonah, on
it. Okay, that's right, it's got the לבונה Levonah, on it. רש"י
Rashi said it's פסול Pasul because since you had a wrong thought,
even though it doesn't qualify as פיגול Pigul because there's another invalidity
going on, it's enough of a wrong thought to make it invalid.
Okay, the נפקא מינה Nafka Mina would be what happens now after
this thought, now you remove the לבונה. Levonah According to תוספות, Tosafot,
the only problem was it had the לבונה, Levonah so now you
remove the לבונה Levonah you're okay. But according to רש"י, Rashi, your
thought was enough to invalidate it and even after you remove the
לבונה, Levonah. it remains invalid.
Did we say the same thing with all the other times when
you
know there was something, another פסול?
Psul? This is the only time we have a reversible פסול. Psul.
So there's nothing really to compare it to. The real question is
going to be whoever heard of a reversible פסול, Psul, so we'll
get to that.
Well the only question is, I mean and this is what I
was struggling with, why isn't it just a regular לא תעשה? Lo
Ta'aseh? You know, and
you're right.
So the, I mean the משנה, mishna, I mean the ברייתא Braita
here learned it out, right?
היא, Hi,
it doesn't really...
I think in the end you're right, in the end it probably
is getting it from the היא Hi word, היא, Hi, only this
way is it kosher. Look, that's not such a problem because like
I said even by the לבונה, Levonah you don't really even understand
the הוה אמינא Hava Amina by לא מיבלע Lo Mivla because how
can you do a קמיצה? kmitzah It'll be קמיצה חסירה. Kemitza Chasirah.
Okay, so partly why I like saying, you know, even with שמן,
so, you know, I mean it just means it's an איסור, so
just take off what you can.
Especially when you have the problem of a קמיצה חסירה, Kemitza Chasirah,
right, then you could suggest those things. But presumably it's learning it
from the word היא. Hi. Okay, so that's what it says, is
that if you have your פיגול Pigul thought now, it's not yet,
it doesn't yet become פיגול Pigul because it has the לבונה Levonah
on it. ואם משליקט לבונתה, Ve'im Mishelikat Levontah, if after you remove
the לבונה, Levonah? חישב עליה חוץ למקומו, Chishav Aleha Chutz Limkomo,
then it goes back to being kosher. חישב עליה חוץ למקומו פסול
ואין בו כרת. Chishav Aleha Chutz Limkomo Pasul Ve'ein Bo Karet.
So if your thought was a wrong place, that invalidates without כרת.
Karet. חוץ לזמנו, Chutz Lizmano, wrong time, that's a פיגול Pigul thought.
פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. Pigul Vechayavin Alav Karet. It is, it becomes
פיגול. Pigul. Now how is this to prove our point? Very simple,
because you were trying to argue, the response is, that you don't
actually have to remove the לבונה. levonah, As long as the לבונה
levonah is not absorbed, it's sufficient for the קרבן korban to be
kosher, right? That's the argument. So here it's very clear because according
to you what, I mean תוספות Tosafot really already asks this. How
could you think you don't have to remove the לבונה? levonah The
משנה mishna, says remove the לבונה, levonah the ברייתא Braita says remove
the לבונה. levonah? So maybe we would have thought that that's just
a מצוה, Mitzvah, but בדיעבד, Bedi'avad, what he's suggesting is it's kosher
even without removing the לבונה levonah, since it doesn't get absorbed. Right?
Because he gives a case where it's impossible to remove the לבונה,
levonah, it's ground up and he wants to suggest it's still kosher.
So according to him, the idea is that yes you're supposed to
remove the לבונה, levona but even if you can't, maybe it remains
kosher. So here it's clear not that way. Here it's clear that
your פיגול Pigul thought has no meaning until the לבונה levona is
removed. So you see that as long as the לבונה levona remains
mixed up, it is considered פסול. Pasul. So once we see that
as long as the לבונה levona is mixed up it's פסול, Pasul,
obviously if it's impossible to remove, it's gonna remain פסול. Pasul. Okay,
so this is how we've answered the question. All these things talk
about removing the לבונה. levona? Until the לבונה levona. is removed, it's
פסול. Pasul. Once the לבונה levona. is removed, it's kosher. It's not
about being absorbed. Even if it's not absorbed, it has to be
removed. If it can't be removed, it remains פסול. Pasul. Fine.
Yeah. Is it only לבונה? levona, What if you throw mint in
there or anything?
So that's a very good question. So you don't transgress. It's a
negative prohibition: ולא תשים עליה שמן לא יתן עליה לבונה. v'lo tasim
aleha shemen lo yiten aleha levonah. The question that you do have
to ask, and that's sort of what I was saying to you
before, was that how do you, why don't you have a קומץ
חסר? kometz chasair? Right? Why don't you say your קמיצה kmitzah. is
lacking, it's not full of all the right ingredients, it's got a
little of the other ingredients? And so I don't know the full
answer, because to some degree, you know, in the past we suggested
adding other ingredients, like we said you could add water to this,
water is never said in the תורה. Torah. And maybe that we
learned out from other מנחות menachos that you know, where also we
assume water, even though it's not written. But remember the גמרא Gemara
for example had suggested fruit juices, and the only problem it had
with that was whether fruit juice could be מחמיץ machmitz or not
מחמיץ. machmitz. So it's not so clear to me. I mean, logically
my intuition would be that anything not explicitly mentioned is a foreign
ingredient, and if it doesn't invalidate directly, at least indirectly it means
that you don't have a קומץ חסר. kometz chasair. But I don't
know the answer. The test would be a מנחת כהנים. Minchas Kohanim.
מנחת כהנים Minchas Kohanim you don't have a קמיצה. kmitzah. So the
question would be let's say you added other ingredients to a מנחת
כהנים, Minchas Kohanim, right? That I don't know. That I would actually
say might be כשר. kasher. What my intuitively although I could look
into it, I would say that if you add an extraneous ingredient,
it certainly makes it a קומץ חסירה kometz chasaira because you don't
have the full, you know, your קומץ kometz is lacking the full
amount of the right ingredients. But a מנחת כהנים Minchas Kohanim if
it’s not שמן or לבונה, levona, who knows? Maybe it is כשר.
kasher I'd have to look into it. Okay, so now we have
that. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to turn its attention to
the question of this very bizarre phenomenon that it becomes פסול pasul
and you can make it כשר kasher again. Okay, and again the
way we're saying it based on how the רבנן explained it in
דף י"ט, daf yud tes, it’s not just that technically you couldn't
take the קמיצה. kmitza? We're calling it פסול. pasul. How does it
become פסול pasul and כשר kasher again? Don't we have a principle
known as what, Michael?
Something that's becomes פסול? pasul?
Oh, you're saying נראה ונדחה? nireh v'nidcheh? דחויי. dichuy.
דחויי. dichuy. Isn't it נדחה? nidcheh? For a while it was פסול.
pasul. How does it become כשר kasher again?
So if a כהן kohein is married to a wife that I'm
not allowed to be with, wouldn't they be...
דחויי dichuy is not about people. דחויי dichuy is about objects, and
it might even not be about live objects בעלי חיים, ba'alei chayim,
but certainly is about inanimate objects. Okay, so how can it be
פסול pasul as a קרבן and then כשר kasher again? That's the
גמרא's Gemara question. So let's take a look.
Now this is a very interesting גירסא girsa of the גמרא. Gemara.
I'll read it the way we have it and then I'll tell
you what תוספות Tosafot says. Here's the way we have it: ותהוי
פח. v'tehevei pach. Why isn't when the לבונה levona, is on it
like a פח, pach, like a, like a vessel which רש"י Rashi
says like oil, meaning why when the לבונה levona is on it,
isn't it like oil spilled on it which totally invalidates it? Ground
up לבונה levona. or just regular לבונה? levona, Even the regular לבונה,
levona, this last ברייתא braita that we quoted. ואמאי פסלה במחשבה? v'amai
pasla b'machshavah? Why did the מחשבה machshavah even for the invalidate, the
פיגול pigul thought מחשבה machshavah invalidate? Even though it didn't make it
פיגול, pigul, at least invalidated. How does it have the power to
invalidate? If it was פסול, pasul, the thought should have done nothing.
Okay? דחויי הוא. dichuy hu. It was נדחה nidcheh and it should
not do anything. That's a very complicated question. ותהוי פח v'tehevei pach
etc., why not just say it's דחויי? dichuy? How does the thing
stop being כשר kasher and become כשר kasher again? So תוספות Tosafot
actually says this is an amazing sort of, if you're an academic
תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says the original גירסא girsa of the גמרא
Gemara was ותהוי דחויי. v'tehevei dichuy. That was it. Let it be
דחויי. dichuy. Let it be pushed away. How does it become כשר
kasher again? Then somebody came in and glossed to explain it in
the words ותהוי דחויי v'tehevei dichuy in the margin and wrote what
was the question: אמאי פסלה במחשבה, amai pasla b'machshavah, why did the
מחשבה machshavah invalidate? Which תוספות Tosafot says what's the question? Forget the
מחשבה. machshavah. The question is how does it become invalid and then
become valid again? And then he wrote, he wrote פירוש. peirush. Here,
it's an explanation to the גמרא: Gemara: אמאי פסלה במחשבה. amai pasla
b'machshavah. And some later person thought the word פירוש peirush פ"י pei
yud with a slash was the word
פח. pach. תוספות Tosafot has a whole explanation of how this גירסא
girsa got this way. תוספות Tosafot says the גירסא girsa is ותהוי
דחויי, v'tehevei dichuy, let it just be דחויי. dichuy. But somebody stuck
in the words, why is מחשבה machshavah a problem? פירוש, peirush, and
פירוש peirush became פח pach and the whole thing. So you can
go look at this תוספות Tosafot ותהוי דחויי v'tehevei dichuy if you
want to see a real academic תוספות, Tosafot, where he recreates how
the text got this way. Anyway, so let's just deal with תוספות's
Tosafot version. Let it be דחויי. dichuy. How does something stop being
good and become good again?
ותהוי דחויי. v'tehevei dichuy. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says,
חטאת קרי רחמנא, chatas karei rachmana, because the פסוק pasuk that told
us that it remains good even with the לבונה, levona, חטאת היא,
chatas hi, is telling us that because it can be fixed, it's
going to retain its status of a חטאת. You're right, it is
bizarre. It is in this middle stage where now it's פסול pasul
but it'll be כשר kasher. later, but because the תורה Torah insists
that it's called a חטאת, it's telling us that it does not
get, it's not נדחה, nidcheh, it's not totally pushed off. Now that
is implicitly for the reason you can fix it, which is what
we're about to see. ורבא אמר, v'Rava amar, הא מני חננא המצרי
היא. ha mani Chanana HaMitzri hi. This is חננא המצרי Chanana HaMitzri
דלית ליה דחויי, d'leis lei dichuy, and he never holds that דחויי
dichuy is a problem. דתניא, d'tanya, חננא המצרי אומר, Chanana HaMitzri omer,
by יום כפור, Yom Kippur, that let's say the שעיר המשתלח seir
hamishtaleach died, what what do you do and you already have the
blood of the other שעיר seir that you're in the middle of
doing the sprinkling. for, so what do you do? So he says:
אפילו דם בכוס, afilu dam bekos, even if the blood is in
the vessel, מביא חבירו שלו בהגרלה, meivi chaveiro shelo behagrala, you bring
another goat if the שעיר המשתלח sa'ir hamishtaleach died without doing the
lot. How do you do lot if one of them is in
blood? Okay, so you don't do the lot, you just bring another
goat and say that's now the new שעיר המשתלח, sa'ir hamishtaleach, ומזווג
לו u-mezaveg lo and you partner it with the blood. So there's
a blood for a while it was נדחה nidcha until you had
the other goat picked out, this blood was pushed away, and nevertheless
you can use it now that you fixed the problem. So you
see, there are those that say דחוי dichui is not a problem
and we would be going according to that opinion. רב אשי אמר,
Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says: no, even without חנניא
המצרי Chananya HaMitzri and even without a special פסוק, pasuk, there's a
reason this is not דחוי. dichui. Why not? כל שבידו לא הוי
דחוי. kol she-beyado lo havei dichui. Anything you can fix is not
דחוי. dichui. If it's totally in your control, it never really gets
pushed aside. Okay, the idea of דחוי dichui is not just that
it's invalid, but if it's invalid it almost gets like rejected. Something
that could be: oh wait, I can just fix it, oh, problem,
no problem, I'll just fix it. Okay, that never really got rejected.
It was always seen as something that has just a little, a
something that can be fixed. Now, of course, the question is what
constitutes בידו? beyado? Is going running and getting another goat בידו? beyado?
I mean, which, how much בידו beyado is בידו? beyado? But this
was very easy. You put some לבונה levona on it, no problem,
just scoop the לבונה levona, off, right, it's not דחוי. dichui. It's
sort of like, it's sort of like the two-second rule, you know
exactly what I'm talking about, right? You drop the nipple of a
bottle on the floor, you pick it up, you blow on it,
two seconds, didn't really happen. Five-second rule. Okay, I'm being more מחמיר.
machmir. Anyway, five-second rule.
Five seconds.
All right, five-second rule.
Anyway, so that's a big deal, it's over double.
Okay, so that's what he says. That's not דחוי. dichui. That's why
it remains כשר. kasher Now of course, while it's still there it's
a problem, but there's an idea of seeing the problem from the
very beginning as being just temporary and fixable and therefore not enough
to push the thing sort of off the center stage. Okay. אמר
רב אדא, Amar Rav Ada, so רב אדא Rav Ada says: כוותיה
דרב אשי מסתברא, ke-vasei de-Rav Ashi mistabra,
it makes sense like רב אשי, Rav Ashi, that this is a
בידו beyado that it's never considered דחוי. dichui. דמאן שמיע ליה דאית
ליה
דחויין, De-man shemi'a lei de-is lei dechuyin, who normally is concerned with
דחוי? dichui? רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתנן,
De-tenan, and we learned in the משנה mishna by again this case
of the goats on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, ועוד אמר רבי יהודה,
ve-od amar Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said: נשפך הדם ימות
המשתלח, nishpach ha-dam yamusa ha-mishtaleach, if the blood is spilled you have
to let the
משתלח mishtaleach die, because you now can't get another pair for it
because this was pushed off. מת המשתלח ישפך הדם. Meis ha-mishtaleach yishapeich
ha-dam. If the משתלח mishtaleach dies you have to spill the blood,
again because it for a while cannot be used. So you see
that he holds of a דחוי dichui problem. ואילו היכא דבידו, Ve-ilu
heicha de-beyado, but we know that when it's in your control to
fix it, תניא, tanya, we taught a ברייתא, beraita, רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, כוס היה ממלא מדם התערובות, kos haya memalei mi-dam
ha-ta'aruvos, that on פסח Pesach
after they brought all the קרבן פסחים korban Pesachs at the end
of the day, they would fill up a vessel from the blood
that's mixed on the floor of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Why?
וזרקו זריקה אחת כנגד היסוד. ve-zarko zerika achas keneged ha-yesod.
And they would do one last throwing on the base of the
מזבח. mizbe'ach, Why? Because maybe somebody's blood, some somebody's קרבן פסח korban
Pesach accidentally spilled, never got thrown on the מזבח, mizbe'ach it's mixed
up with all the other bloods, so you pick it all up
and you throw it again and therefore you're okay. So you see,
he holds that even though there was a while it wasn't used,
if you can fix it, it's not דחוי, dichui, even though in
principle he holds of דחוי. dichui. Now there's two interesting points here.
Number one is, the case by the goat was also בידו, beyado,
right? I mean, go get another goat. Why is it not בידו?
beyado? Why is that considered דחוי? dichui? So unless you say that
the problem there was because you need to start with a matched
pair when you get one to start, but then it's not a
דחוי dichui problem, then the problem is because it wasn't a matched
pair to begin with.
So
it shows you that not every בידו beyado is equivalent. Some things
are very quick fixes and some things are more complicated fixes and
not every בידו beyado is equivalent. The other interesting thing is, it's
not clear to me why the blood on the floor of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is considered to be דחוי. dichui. That blood
was never unusable. If that blood was caught in a כלי שרת,
kli shareis, which is what we have to be talking about, and
then it spilled. So
how is that any less usable because it's not right now in
a כלי שרת, kli shareis, I guess would be the point.
So I'm just saying that what makes it not usable? Pick it
up and throw it. It's not exactly the same as לבונה levonah
which is פסול pasul while the לבונה levonah is there. Maybe the
point is that while it's on the floor it's not in a
כלי שרת kli shareis and you have to get it on the
מזבח mizbe'ach with a כלי שרת, kli shareis, not straight from the
floor. That's probably the idea of להתקדש ריצפה. le-hiskadesh ritzpa. What? Yeah,
but there's anyway there's no way you can bring it to the
מזבח mizbeach in its form, you have to get it in a
different form, maybe that's the point.
Maybe there was dirt on the floor or something else that would
be mixed up?
No, but then we've never solved that problem. Presumably the only problem,
other than it has yet to be brought, is that it's not
in a כלי שרת. kli shareis. Okay, so anyway, that's how you
see that בידו beyado fixes things. Okay. Now we go, and that's
why this מנחה mincha. can become כשר again and it's not דחוי.
dichui. Okay. אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, now we get back
to the... how you transgress and we talk about the שיעור. Shiur.
So let's take a look. אמר רבי יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so Rabbi Yitzchak
bar Yosef said in the name of Rabbi Yochanan: נתן משהו שמן,
Nasan Mashehu Shemen, how much you have to put on how much
in order to transgress. So even if it's the smallest amount of
oil, על גבי כזית מנחה, al gabei kezayis mincha, as long as
the amount of the מנחה mincha? is a כזית kezayis worth, פסול,
pasul, you've invalidated it. It might be like a קמיצה? kmitza, Okay,
well let's take a look. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? What's the reason?
לא ישים, it says do not place, and שימה sima is כל
שהוא, kol shehu, even the smallest amount. To place, there's no sense
of a minimum amount to place something. It could mean even to
put a drop of something on, so there's no amount of oil.
And how do you know that the מנחה mincha. has to be
a כזית? kezayis? עליה, on it, עד דאיכא שיעורא, ad de'ika shiura,
it has to be some size of significance. Now Michael says maybe
it's a קמיצה, kmitza but remember, this is not just about doing
the קמיצה kmitza and being מקריב makriv it, it could be on
the part of the מנחה mincha, that you're not doing the קמיצה
kmitza on. So therefore מנחה mincha also has significance as something that's
eaten, right? That's what the כהנים kohanim are going to do to
the rest of it. So therefore we assume the smaller of the
שיעורים shiurim which is a כזית. kezayis. Okay, Michael says a קמיצה
kemitza. would have been possible, but it's not limited to the קומץ
kometz and we assume a כזית. kezayis. That's how much you need
for the prohibition of oil. ואמר רבי יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי
יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef Amar Rabbi Yochanan, now how about
the prohibition of לבונה? levonah, Wait, let's just do the לבונה. levonah
נתן כזית לבונה על גבי משהו מנחה פסול. Nasan kezayis levona al
gabei mashehu mincha pasul. We reverse it when it comes to the
לבונה. levonah It has to be a כזית kezayis worth of לבונה,
levonah? not a משהו, mashehu, on how much of a מנחה? mincha.
Even the smallest amount. Why? Why are we reversing it? מאי טעמא?
Mai taama? לא יתן כתיב, Lo yiten ksiv, do not place. So
placing, as opposed to שים, sim, I don't know, there's not good
different English words. שים Sim is maybe, I don't know, putting, ויתן
v'yiten is more like giving. Don't give on it. So that's more
the idea. To give
onto something, עד דאיכא נתינה, ad de'ika nesina,
you have to give something of significance. If I gave you something,
suggests it was a thing, there was something of substance. So it
has to be something of substance, it has to be a כזית.
kezayis. Now how do you get on even a כל שהוא? kol
shehu? עליה, on it. So how does that tell you even a
smallest amount of מנחה? mincha? Before we said it means something of
significance. So דף ס עמוד א, Daf Samech Amud Alef, הוי ריבוי
אחר ריבוי, Havei ribui achar ribui, it's a, you know, it's an
increase after an increase. It already said עליה by the oil, don't
put on it oil, and on it means something of significance. Now
it's saying don't give on it לבונה, levonah. and on it again
means something of significance. It's making a double demand, so we have
our general principle, אין ריבוי אחר ריבוי אלא למעט, Ein ribui achar
ribui ela lema'et, that a double status where we're insisting on it
yet again, we actually mean it doesn't have to be so big,
and therefore even if you put it on a small amount of
a מנחה. mincha Okay, so when it comes to the oil, a
little bit on a כזית, kezayis, when it comes to לבונה, levonah.
it has to be a כזית kezayis worth because of נתינה nesina
to give, but even on a small amount of a מנחה. mincha
We'll read to the two dots and then we'll hear a question,
Michael? Okay. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika d'amrei, some say, אמר רבי יצחק בר
יוסף בעי רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef baei Rabbi Yochanan,
that Rabbi Yochanan actually asked a question about this. Once he's now
established that the לבונה levonah. is a כזית kezayis because יתן to
give means something of significance, a כזית, kezayis, he wants to go
back and say maybe that should inform the prohibition of the oil.
So he says נתן משהו שמן על גבי כזית מנחה מהו? Nasan
mashehu shemen al gabei kezayis mincha mahu? What is the story if
you only do a little bit of oil on even a כזית
kezayis of a מנחה? mincha מי בעינן שימה כנתינה? Mi bayinan sima
k'nesina? Do we translate the word שימה sima to place through the
lens of נתינה nesina to give? And the same way נתינה nesina
to give means a כזית, kezayis, שימה sima also means a כזית,
kezayis, so you'd have to do a כזית kezayis worth of שמן?
או לא? O lo? Or do we say no, שימה sima means
any amount, even a כל שהוא? kol shehu? תיקו, Teiku, so we
don't know. So it's clear that נתינה nesina means a כזית. kezayis.
The question is, שימה sima normally can mean a small amount, but
in the context of נתינה, nesina, maybe it means a כזית. kezayis.
One more comment and then we'll hear what Michael wants to ask.
The idea that נתינה nesina is a כזית, kezayis, תוספות Tosafos has
a very interesting question of do we always say that or not.
He discusses other cases. First of all, רש"י Rashi says, where do
we know נתינה nesina is a כזית kezayis anyway, giving it a
כזית? kezayis? Actually from this last week's פרשה. parsha. This last week's
פרשה parsha it said that if somebody eats קודש בשגגה, kodesh b'shigaga,
eats sanctified things in error, which חז"ל Chazal say means he ate
תרומה teruma that he should not because it belongs to the כהן,
Kohen ונתן לכהן את הקודש, venasan l'kohen es hakodesh, he gives the
כהן Kohen the קודש kodesh and חז"ל Chazal understand what that means:
if I accidentally ate a כהן's Kohen תרומה, teruma, I have to
give him food in exchange, and that food then becomes automatically תרומה.
teruma. That my compensation becomes תרומה. teruma. And since the problem there
was was that I ate it, and I'm giving him something therefore
that can be eaten, we understand that נתינה nesina not only has
to be food in that context, but it had to be a
כזית. kezayis. So that's where we learn out נתינה nesina is in
כזית. kezayis. תוספות Tosafos deals with other cases where the concern might
more be about monetary issues, and נתינה nesina might be a פרוטה,
peruta, not a כזית. kezayis. Right? It's always a question what lens
are you looking at something through? Right? You know what they say?
What is it? Like a cynic knows the, what is it, the
price of everything and value of nothing. Right. So if you're always
looking at something through the lens of how much does it cost,
right, maybe נתינה nesina is it's got to be worth a dollar.
Right? Not everything is about what it costs. Sometimes a thing is
like how
much... So here it's interesting that we're talking about foods and we're
talking about נתינה ככזית *netina ke-kezayit*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* discusses sometimes where
נתינה *netina* might be בפרוטה *b'peruta* depending on our lens. The other
interesting question that תוספות Tosafos, *Tosfos* raises which goes back to a
point we said about a week ago that I just wanted to
repeat is תוספות *Tosfos* says but one minute, we don't say it
by תרומה *teruma*. By תרומה *teruma* it says that you should give
it to the כהן *kohen*. If you look at the first wide
line here on ס"א ע"א *Samech Aleph Amud Aleph*, תוספות *Tosfos* says
like this, and not the first wide line, five lines before the
lines get wide, the line starts with the word בתרומה *b'teruma*. He
says וכ"ת קשה *v'kas kasha* בתרומה *b'teruma* דכתיב *d'chtiv* תתן לו *titen
lo*, give the כהן *kohen* the תרומה *teruma*. אמאי חטה אחת פוטרת
את et הכרי *amai chita achas poteres es hakari*? Why do we
say even one little grain exempts the whole big, you know, what?
A heap, a mound of grain. אמאי לא בעי כזית כנתינה דשמעתין
*amai lo baei kezayit k'nesina d'shmatin*? Let's require a כזית *kezayit*. How
are you giving the כהן *kohen* anything of substance? And as I
told you,
תוספות *Tosfos* doesn't have an answer.
And anyway, as I told you about a week ago, there are
those that explain that there actually are two מצוות *mitzvos* of תרומה
*teruma*. One is to exempt the grain, to make the grain no
longer טבל *tevel*, and there even the tiniest amount. But there's a
separate מצוה *mitzvah* to give something to the כהן *kohen*. And to
give something to the כהן *kohen*, it actually does have to be
something of substance, and it cannot be a tiny amount. And to
see that there's two aspects to the מצוה *mitzvah* of תרומה *teruma*.
So here it's interesting that תוספות *Tosfos* raises that question. He doesn't
give that answer. He sees it all as one, and he doesn't
leave his question answered. Michael, you had a question.
Yeah, I was going to say was that
when
we're saying on a כזית *kezayit*, you know, it seems like that's
still too small because what are you going to do with the
כזית *kezayit*? Like you can't even do קמיצה kmitza *kemitza* out of
that.
Because the כזית *kezayit* is... because the קמיצה kmitza, *kemitza* is שני
זיתים *shnei zeisim*. So I think you wouldn't even have done anything.
But who says it's the קמיצה kmitza *kemitza*? מנחה mincha *mincha* can
also be eaten. The רמב"ם *Rambam* says the מנחה mincha, *mincha*...
but you can't eat the שירים *shirayim* until you do the קמיצה
kmitza *kemitza*. Like קמיצה kmitzah, *kemitza* has to be, you know, it
has to be a קמיצה kmitzah, שיעור *kemitza shiur*. Right. So what
sort of, like, you know,
if since you're not making...
you're doing something wrong to the מנחה mincha *mincha*, you're saying that
since the only transgression is before the קמיצה kmitzah *kemitza* anyway, by
the שירים *shirayim* we learned you don't transgress, why don't I measure
it by the קמיצה kmitzah *kemitza*? Okay, but at least you've done
something of substance that you've ruined a part of the edible part
of the מנחה mincha
*mincha*. But you know, so I understand, anyway, normally we'll just assume
the minimum, you know.
But if we're worrying about a קמיצה kmitzah חסר *kemitza chaser*, it
should be even the littlest amount on the littlest amount because,
you know, you put שמן *shemen* on the whole idea that you
did it only on a כזית *kezayit* of it means you separated
a part out and you're only doing it or you limited it
to a part of the vessel. So that part might be the
part that I do the קמיצה kmitzah. *kemitza* on. That part I
might do the יציקה *yitzika*.
No, I put a little bit on an itty bitty bit and
it gets all mixed up and, you know, I don't know where
I
do my קמיצה kmitzah *kemitza*. Why do I have to look at
it as though it's functioning relating to the קמיצה *kemitza* of the
מנחה mincha, *mincha*? Why not look at it as it is relating
to the edible part of the מנחה mincha, *mincha*? That seems to
be the assumption.
Yes you can... oh, you can't have both though, that's what I'm
saying.
Yes you can. The whole point here is you didn't put it
on the whole שיעור *shiur*. You put it on a separate... you
separated out a piece or you put it at one edge of
the vessel, so maybe that's the part I'm going
to... Then you don't have... then you don't have the whole problem.
The whole problem is you only put it on a small part
of the מנחה mincha *mincha*. You have to define a small part.
Maybe you come back, you don't know where it is.
I don't know why you're assuming that's not the case. Okay. תנו
רבנן *Tanu rabanan*. נתן עליה שמן על שיריה *Nasan aleha shemen al
shireha*. Okay, so now the end of the משנה mishna *mishna* says
if you would oil on the remnant it's כשר *kasher*. תנו רבנן
*Tanu rabanan*: לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן *Lo yasim aleha shemen
v'lo yiten*. Do not put oil on it and don't put on
it לבונה levonah. *levona*. יכול בשני כהנים kohanim *Yachol b'shnei kohanim*? Maybe
it's requiring two כהנים kohanim, *kohanim*. Now what's the הוה אמינא *hava
amina* it would require two כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*? So I'll give you
the way תוספות *Tosfos* says it. תוספות *Tosfos* is different than רש"י
*Rashi*. תוספות *Tosfos* says the question here is if I do the
same thing on one מנחה mincha *mincha*. First I put שמן *shemen*.
Remember what happened if I put שמן *shemen*? What did it make
the מנחה mincha *mincha*? פסול pasul *pasul*. Now I put לבונה *levona*
on. Have I transgressed? Maybe the same way I don't transgress if
I make a פסול *pasul* מנחה mincha. *mincha* מחמץ *mechameitz*, right? Because
it's already... because it's already פסול *pasul*, maybe I don't transgress if
I put לבונה *levona* on a מנחה mincha. *mincha* that I already
put שמן *shemen* on. Or maybe not. The תורה Torah *Torah* links
them. Maybe the same way you can do מחמץ אחר מחמץ *mechameitz
achar mechameitz*, if you continue to make it חמץ *chametz* even though
it's already חמץ *chametz* you transgress, maybe לבונה *levona* after שמן *shemen*
I would transgress. Maybe if it was פסול *pasul* for some other
reason, it was פגול *pigul*, it was יוצא *yotzei*, I wouldn't. But
if it's שמן *shemen* and לבונה *levona*, maybe I transgress. So that's
the question. Do I need... תוספות *Tosfos* says when it says two
כהנים *kohanim* it doesn't mean two כהנים *kohanim*, it means two מנחות
menachos. *minchos*. Like two כהנים *kohanim* we envision that each כהן *kohen*
with his מנחה mincha. *mincha* would take ideally with a מנחה mincha
*mincha*. So יכול בשני כהנים *Yachol b'shnei kohanim*, maybe I only transgress
these things if we're dealing with two separate כהנים *kohanim*, which means
two separate מנחות minchas, *minchos*. תלמוד לומר עליה talmud lomar aleha, *Talmud
lomar aleha*. גופה של מנחה mincha, הכתוב מדבר *Gufa shel mincha haksav
medaber*. On it, on the מנחה mincha? *mincha* itself, meaning even on
the same מנחה mincha *mincha* you put the שמן *shemen*, don't put
the לבונה *levona*, and yes you will transgress if you put the
לבונה *levona* on the מנחה mincha *mincha* with the שמן *shemen* even
if it's the same מנחה mincha *mincha*. So that's one read of
תוספות *Tosfos*. The other read he has at the end means the
exact opposite, that no, עליה *aleha* only on one individual מנחה mincha
*mincha*, but would you transgress, you know,
that each prohibition is for a separate מנחה *mincha*, but if it's
the same מנחה *mincha* you don't transgress once you do one after
the other. But for תוספות *Tosfos* that's the issue here. Do you
transgress if you do לבונה *levona* after שמן *shemen* once it's already
פסול *pasul*? And I would say if you read it that way
the simple answer is is that yes, you do transgress. Even if
it's only one מנחה *mincha* you will transgress both. Okay, תנו רבנן
*Tanu rabanan*. ולא
בכהן v'lo b'kohein, וגופא דכל מנחה קמיירי v'gufo d'chol mincha kamairi ולא
בכהן, not with a different כהן which here תוספות takes to mean
not with a different מנחה. יכול לא יתן כלי אגבי כלי, yachol
lo yitein k'li agabei k'li, maybe you can't even put oil in
a vessel on top of your מנחה, ואם נתן פסל, and maybe
if you did it would invalidate. תלמוד לומר עליה, on it, directly.
בגופה של מנחה קמיירי, b'gufah shel mincha kamairi, don't put the oil
on the מנחה as opposed to don't put the oil in a
vessel and the vessel on the מנחה. So not only do you
not invalidate, you also do not transgress. But according to תוספות, the
interesting question here although he had two variations of what the answer
is, is whether you transgress, if it already became פסול because of
your שמן, you could continue to transgress because of the לבונה. Okay,
let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishna So that
was two משניות Mishnayos that wrapped up with which things get oil,
which things get לבונה, and so on, the basic ingredients. Now we
talk less about the ingredients and more about the procedures, and what
do you do with the מנחה? So the תורה Torah says that
you take the מנחה והגישה אל המזבח, v'higishah el hamizbeach, that you
bring it to the altar. We're going to say you take the
מנחה and you touch it to a corner of the altar. Does
this apply by all מנחות minchas or not? So let's take a
look. And some מנחות minchas also get waved. So that's now going
to be the focus here, הגשה hagasha and תנופה. tenufa. יש טעונות
הגשה ואין טעונות תנופה, yesh teunot hagasha v'ein teunot tenufa,
there are some that are touched to the מזבח mizbeach, but do
not get waved. הגשה ותנופה, hagasha v'tenufa, some get touched and waved.
תנופה ולא הגשה, tenufa v'lo hagasha, things that get waved and not
touched, that will include even non-מנחות, menachot. but okay. לא תנופה ולא
הגשה, lo tenufa v'lo hagasha, neither get waved nor get touched to
the altar. ואלו טעונות הגשה ואין טעונות תנופה, v'eilu teunot hagasha v'ein
teunot tenufa, now here are the ones that get הגשה hagasha and
not תנופה. tenufa. Interesting, remember when it came to oil and לבונה,
we first mentioned the ones that had both. Here we're mentioning the
one that only has הגשה. hagasha. You know why? Because we want
to start with the big list. So when it came to oil
and לבונה, the standard was oil and לבונה and you had ten
things. Here when it comes to waving and הגשה, hagasha, the standard
is just הגשה, hagasha, waving is an exception. Why waving? We're going
to define it in the גמרא, Gemara, but it's an up and
down and back and forth. Okay, but we'll get to it in
the גמרא. Gemara.
Hands?
Yeah. In the כלי.
Yeah, not, not the מנחה's in the כלי, the כלי is in
the hands. Correct. Okay, we'll discuss it in the גמרא, Gemara, but
okay. So here the standard is הגשה hagasha and therefore without תנופה,
tenufa, and therefore that's the one we list first and again there
are going to be ten. So let's count. Okay. ואלו טעונות הגשה
ואין טעונות תנופה, v'eilu teunot hagasha v'ein teunot tenufa, מנחת הסולת, minchat
hasolet, the simple one of flour and just plain flour and oil.
המחבת והמרחשת, hamachavat v'hamarcheshet, the frying pan, the deep frying pan. החלות
והרקיקין, hachalot v'harekikin,
and the חלות chalot and רקיקין rekikin are two variations of מאפה
תנור, maafeh tanur, things that are baked in an oven. The תורה
Torah says חלות מצות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן, chalot matzot
b'lulot bashamen u'rekikei matzot meshuchim bashamen, one which is more bread-like, the
other which is more wafer-like. So we have סולת, מחבת, מרחשת, חלות,
רקיקין, solet, machavat, marcheshet, chalot, rekikin, that's five. These are the same
as the others? Same list as the others. Five, based on the
first four מנחות menachot, mentioned in the תורה Torah in ויקרא, Vayikra,
but we understand that the חלות chalot and רקיקין rekikin are variations
of מאפה תנור. maafeh tanur. So that's five. Okay. מנחת כהנים, minchat
kohanim, even if it's brought by the כהנים and none get eaten.
מנחת כהן משיח, minchat kohein mashiach, or the כהן גדול, kohein gadol,
half in the morning, half in the evening. Also it's obligatory and
nothing gets eaten. Nevertheless, that is הגשה hagasha without תנופה. tenufa. Same
הלכה. halacha. All of these are private מנחות. Okay, until now. The
five variations of a normal individual, כהנים, כהן משיח, kohein mashiach, מנחת
נכרים, minchat nochrim, non-Jews. עובדי כוכבים? ovdei kochavim? עובדי כוכבים, ovdei kochavim,
that was more of an, yeah, עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim is never
the original גרסא. girsa.
Why would it be קיסר? Keisar?
I have no idea. Okay, of non-Jews. מנחת נשים, minchat nashim, women,
also fascinating why it gets included. There is no different halachic status
to a מנחה of women. There is to a קרבן that you
don't do סמיכה, smicha, not to a מנחה, but for some reason
it's mentioning it, as I mentioned yesterday, I think it's just to
get to the number of ten. Because now we're up to nine.
And מנחת חוטא, minchat chotei, a מנחה of a sinner, all of
those get הגשה. hagasha. Now here is where the list becomes a
little different than yesterday. Even Michael, yesterday what was it different? You
didn't have מנחת חוטא. minchat chotei What did you have yesterday?
We had מנחת עומר, minchat omer, מנחת נסכים. minchat nesachim.
מנחת עומר, minchat omer, we had עומר. omer. Why? Because there's a
different rule that dictates. The rule that dictates about what gets
הגשה, hagasha, specifically you know...
I know. The rule that dictates what gets הגשה, hagasha, what gets
touched to the מזבח, mizbeach. is a מנחה of which part is
actually burnt on the מזבח. mizbeach, So a normal מנחה, everything is
burnt, a קומץ. kometz. Even מנחת כהנים, minchat kohanim, the entire thing
is burnt.
If that something is getting burnt on the מזבח, mizbeach. it gets
הגשה. hagasha. Okay? So therefore you have the last case of מנחת
חוטא, minchat chotei. some of it got burnt, right? It gets burnt
if you do a קמיצה. Therefore it's going on the מזבח. mizbeach.
Why does עומר omer not in here? Well, first of all, the
answer is because עומר omer gets waved. So עומר omer yes, a
part does get burnt, it does get הגשה, hagasha, but it's in
the special category of having both. Okay, that's why it's not in
this list. But it does include מנחת חוטא, because here it's not
the question of oil and לבונה, which is specifically not about the
sinner's מנחה, it's about the rule of הגשה. hagasha. And הגשה hagasha
is anytime a part of the מנחה gets burnt, it gets הגשה.
hagasha. The only reason עומר omer is not here is because an
עומר omer also gets waved. So let's... keep on going, those are
the ten things that get only הגשה. hagasha. Now we go on.
רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: מנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח אין
בהם הגשה. Minchat Kohanim uMinchat Kohen Mashiach ein bahem hagasha. He says
though the מנחה of כהנים does not get הגשה, hagasha, oh something
gets burned, for him that's not enough.
It's not enough for him that some part of it gets burned,
it has to be only when when a קמיצה gets burned, when
not all of it gets burned. When some gets burned and some
gets eaten. וכל שאין בהם קמיצה אין בהם הגשה. V'chol she'ein bahem
kmitza ein bahem hagasha. There's no קמיצה, there's no הגשה. hagasha. It's
true the מנחת כהנים Minchat Kohanim it all gets burned, that doesn't
work for me. It had to be the קמיצה is burned and
the rest is eaten. So he has a different standard. So when
it comes to קמיצה before we go when it comes to הגשה
hagasha before we get to תנופה, tnufa, that's based on the principle
that a part of it gets burned, so to exclude for example
like what would be a good thing that's not burned, שתי הלחם.
Shtei HaLechem. Nothing gets burned, right? Or the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim.
What goes with the לחם הפנים? Lechem HaPanim? Only the לבונה gets
put on the מזבח. mizbeach. The שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem only the
lambs go on the מזבח. mizbeach, Nothing gets burned, there's no הגשה.
hagasha. And there's a question: what if it all gets burned? רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no הגשה, hagasha, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
says yes. Okay, something else. Now there is something not on this
list that does get burned, that is מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. That's
right, the one that comes with the animals that all gets burned.
That's not on the list because that doesn't come on its own
accord. So the basic implicit principle here is it gets burned and
it comes on its own. Comes on its own excludes מנחת נסכים.
Minchat Nesachim. Gets burned excludes things like שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, I'm
sorry, like or לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim which don't get burned, only
the לבונה gets burned. And then the whole debate is about the
מנחת כהנים, Minchat Kohanim, what happens if it all gets burned? Does
that also get הגשה? hagasha? Let's go ahead. We had all the
list
in one משנה, I guess now there's more to discuss.
There's more to discuss, right, because then we're going to have to
do the whole תנופה tnufa discussion and yes, there's more to discuss.
So again, I don't know in the original break-up of the משנה,
I haven't checked, but at least the editor of the גמרא Gemara
decided to break this up for more focused discussion. Okay, so we
are of now only looking at the first part of the list.
אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: so רב פפא Rav Papa said,
we had this exact statement of רב פפא Rav Papa yesterday. כל
היכא דתנן עשר תנן. Kol heicha d'tnan esser tnan. Whenever we have
this big list of מנחות, yesterday it was about oil and לבונה,
here it's about הגשה, hagasha, it's always ten מנחות that are listed.
מאי קמשמע לן? Mai kamashma lan? What are you telling me? Of
course, I can count too. לאפוקי מדרבי שמעון L'afokei m'd'Rabbi Shimon to
exclude from רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon דאמר מחצה חלות ומחצה רקיקין יביא,
d'amar mechtza chalos u'mechtza rekikin yavi,
that when you bring the מנחה of מאפה תנור, Ma'afeh Tanur, it
doesn't have to be, rather than saying either ten of one, ten
loaves of one or ten loaves of the other, he actually says
you're allowed to bring five loaves of each, five loaves of the
חלות, chalos, five loaves of the רקיקין, rekikin, or חמש חמש, chamesh
chamesh, or ten of one, ten of the other. Our משנה just
gave the option ten of one, ten of the other. So according
to him there's a third variation. It's not just חלות chalos or
רקיקין, rekikin, it's also חלות chalos and רקיקין. rekikin. So according to
him you'd have eleven on the list, not ten. קמשמע לן דלא.
Kamashma lan d'lo. Our משנה is exactly saying ten, a nice round
number, implicitly rejecting רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that you could bring a
מאפה תנור Ma'afeh Tanur of a combination of five and five. Okay,
fine, that was parenthetical. Let's get now to the core of the
משנה about הגשה. hagasha. מנא
הני מילי? Mina hanei mili? Where do you know this? About which
things get הגשה? hagasha? דתנו רבנן. D'tanu rabanan. Because the Rabbis said.
אילו נאמר. Ilu ne'emar. Had it said. So the פסוק pasuk says
והבאת את המנחה אשר יעשה מאלה לה'. v'heiveita et hamincha asher ye'aseh
me'eileh l'Hashem. This is at the end of where it brings about
bringing the מנחה.
והקריבה אל הכהן והגישה
אל המזבח.
v'hikrivah el
hakohen v'higishah el hamizbeach.
Downstairs, I don't know. Oh, בסדר. beseder. His office is the second
door on the left in PT 10,
right.
So the תורה Torah says at the beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra, ונפש
כי תקריב קרבן מנחה לה' v'nefesh ki takriv korban mincha l'Hashem and
gives you all the variations of the מנחה. And after it gives
you all the variations it tells you how you bring the מנחה.
It says
והבאת את המנחה אשר יעשה מאלה לה' v'heiveita et hamincha asher ye'aseh
me'eileh l'Hashem from any of
these. והקריבה אל הכהן והגישה אל המזבח. v'hikrivah el hakohen v'higishah el
hamizbeach. The כהן brings it to the מזבח, mizbeach. he touches it
to the מזבח. mizbeach. So here it's quite explicit as opposed to
yesterday where we were discussing לבונה and לבונה is only mentioned in
סלת solet in the first one. The חז"ל Chazal assume that it
applies to all. Here the פסוק pasuk is very clear. Whichever type
of מנחה you bring, והגישה אל המזבח, v'higishah el hamizbeach, bring it
to the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, so let's take a look. אילו נאמר
והבאת אשר יעשה מאלה. Ilu ne'emar v'heiveita asher ye'aseh me'eileh. You should
bring, it didn't say you should bring the מנחה, but you should
bring that which you will make לה' l'Hashem to God. והקריבה אל
הכהן והגישה v'hikrivah el hakohen v'higishah and the כהן bring it to
the כהן he'll touch it to the מזבח. mizbeach הייתי אומר אין
לי שטעון הגשה אלא קומץ בלבד. Hayiti omer ein li sheteun hagasha
ela kometz bilvad. I might think it only applies to the קומץ.
kometz. Because only the קומץ kometz is אשר יעשה מאלה לה'. asher
ye'aseh me'eileh l'Hashem. Is only the one going straight to God. So
מנחה מנין? mincha minayin? How do I know it applies to הגשה,
hagasha, the touching to the מזבח applies to the entire מנחה? תלמוד
לומר מנחה. Talmud lomar mincha. It says you shall bring the מנחה
והגישה אל המזבח. v'higishah el hamizbeach. Okay, that's just פשט pshat of
פסוקים psukim so far. מנחת חוטא מנין? Minchat Chotei minayin? Now I
only know that about the four five standard מנחות that are mentioned
at the beginning. How do I know about the מנחה of חטא
chet which is no oil and no לבונה? How do I know
that also does הגשה? hagasha?
תלמוד לומר את המנחה. Talmud lomar et hamincha. The extra את comes
to include even ones not ודין הוא v'din hu, *V'din hu*. Now
I could have learned this out logically.
How do we know that it needs a פסוק pasuk.
*passuk*? Alright, that's always the question. So let's see the logic that's
informing the whole discussion. נאמר הכא מנחה מנחת חובה *Ne'emar hacha mincha
minchat chova* ונאמר הכא מנחת נדבה *v'ne'emar hacha minchat nedava*. So we
have by the individual in the first פרשה *parsha* ויקרא *Vayikra* a
obligatory מנחה *mincha* which is the מנחת חוטא *minchat chote* and we
have a free will מנחה *mincha* which is mentioned first which is
all the variations of the מנחה *mincha*. מה מנחת נדבה טעונה הגשה
hagasha. אף מנחת חובה טעונה הגשה hagasha, *Ma minchat nedava te'una hagasha,
af minchat chova te'una hagasha*. I could have made a logical comparison.
The same way an individual free will מנחה *mincha* gets הגשה hagasha
*hagasha*, I would have assumed by analogy the same is true by
the later מנחה *mincha* in ויקרא *Vayikra* of the obligatory one. Wait
one minute, maybe not? מה למנחת נדבה שכן טעונה שמן ולבונה *Ma
leminchat nedava sheken te'una shemen ulevona*. Obviously they're not the same. The
free will מנחה *mincha* you have oil and לבונה *levona* so of
course it's different from a מנחת חוטא *minchat chote* so maybe only
the נדבה *nedava* gets הגשה hagasha. *hagasha* and not the חובה *chova*.
מנחת סוטה minchat sotah תוכיח *Minchat sota tochiach*. No, I'll prove it
from a מנחת סוטה minchat sotah *minchat sota*. Because a מנחת סוטה
minchat sotah *minchat sota* doesn't get oil, doesn't get לבונה *levona* and
it very explicitly says by the מנחת סוטה minchat sotah *minchat sota*
as we're going to quote later that you touch it to the
מזבח *mizbe'ach*. Yeah, but here you see. Okay, so we'll get to
that. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says you see that even without
oil and לבונה *levona* you do הגשה hagasha. *hagasha*. No, מה למנחת
סוטה Sotah. שכן טעונה תנופה tenufah *Ma leminchat sota sheken te'una tnupha*.
You see that Michael could have written it. The מנחת סוטה minchat
sotah. *minchat sota* requires תנופה *tnupha*, so you can't prove that that
gets הגשה hagasha. *hagasha* anything gets הגשה hagasha, *hagasha* because that's special.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says okay, מנחת נדבה תוכיח *minchat nedava tochiach*.
But I'll prove that תנופה *tnupha* doesn't matter from a free will
מנחה *mincha* which doesn't have תנופה *tnupha*. So this is one of
those cases where there are different characteristics. The underlying commonality is that
they all get הגשה hagasha *hagasha*. וחוזר הדין *Vechozer hadin*, and it
goes back and forth. לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה
כראי זה lo re'i zeh k're'i zeh v'lo re'i zeh k're'i zeh.
*Lo rei zeh k'rei zeh v'lo rei zeh k'rei zeh*. Each one's
distinctive characteristic is not like the other. מנחת סוטה Sotah. *minchat sota*'s
distinctive is that it gets תנופה *tnupha*, מנחת נדבה *minchat nedava* a
normal free will מנחה *mincha*'s distinctive that it gets oil and לבונה
*levona*. But in the end those are not true about the other
case so you eliminate the distinctive characteristics. הצד השווה שבהן *Hatzad hashaveh
shebahen*, in the end the common denominator is תשוו לקמיצה *tishavu likmitza*.
Both of them you do קמיצה *kmitza* on whether it's a סוטה
Sotah *sota* or a מנחת נדבה *minchat nedava*. ותשוו להגשה *V'tishavu lehagasha*,
they get הגשה hagasha. *hagasha*. אף אני אביא מנחת חוטא *Af ani
avi minchat chote*, so I'll include also מנחת *minchat* of a sinner
שתשוו להם לקמיצה ותשוו להם להגשה *shetishavu lahem likmitza v'tishavu lahem lehagasha*.
Since you do קמיצה *kmitza* on it you should also do הגשה
hagasha. *hagasha* on it. So I could have learned it out from
logic. No, here would be the question. מה לצד השווה שבהן שכן
הוכשרו לבוא בעשיר כבעוני *Ma latzad hashaveh shebahen sheken huchshru lavo b'ashir
k'v'oni*. Those types of things whether it's a סוטה Sotah, *sota* or
whether it's free will, even a rich person can bring. A מנחת
חוטא *minchat chote* is only brought by a poor person. The whole
idea of a מנחת חוטא *minchat chote* is a certain type of
a חטאת *chatat*, again very rare type of a חטאת *chatat*, עולה
ויורד *oleh v'yored*, which is varies based on the person's wealth. So
only a poor person can bring a מנחת חוטא *minchat chote*, it's
not similar, it has something that makes it stand out from the
rest. And therefore maybe it doesn't get הגשה hagasha *hagasha*. תאמר במנחת
חוטא שלא הוכשרה לבוא בעשיר כבעוני *Tomar beminchat chote shelo huchshra lavo
b'ashir k'v'oni*? So maybe because it cannot be brought by anybody, it
can only be brought by a poor person, maybe it's different and
it doesn't get הגשה hagasha *hagasha*? That would be a very negative
religious message wouldn't it? Since only a poor, this is only a
poor person's מנחה *mincha* we're not going to do הגשה *hagasha* to
the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. Anyway, thankfully we don't say that. תלמוד לומר *Talmud
lomar*, so that's why the verse has to teach את המנחה *et
hamincha*. The extra את *et* comes to include. So Michael your question
how do I know what את *et* is included, obviously you see
here the גמרא *Gemara* essentially or the ברייתא braita *braita* has shown
its hand. We have a logic which is compelling of to want
to include חוטא *chote*, but because you can technically make a difference
we need that extra word in the פסוק *passuk*. But obviously how
we learn that word is informed by the logic that we're coming
to the פסוק *passuk* with. Okay, let's just do a little bit
more. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר *Rabbi Shimon Omer*, now רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says he focuses on a different part of
the פסוק *passuk*. He's really not disagreeing yet. In the end we're
going to disagree about כהנים *Kohanim*, but he's not disagreeing yet. So
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר והבאת *Rabbi Shimon omer v'heiveta*, it says
and you shall bring. לרבות מנחת העומר להגשה *Lerabot minchat ha'omer lehagasha*.
So you use the את *et* to include a מנחת *minchat* of
a sinner. We have another מנחה *mincha* we have to include. The
מנחת עומר omer, *minchat omer*. Yeah but doesn't he...
doesn't that need תנופה *tnupha* too? So he's...
yeah but we're not talking about תנופה *tnupha*, we just want to
know הגשה *hagasha*. Okay? So I'm going to use and you shall
bring to include even the מנחת עומר omer, *minchat omer* gets הגשה
*hagasha*. וכן הוא אומר *V'chen hu omer*, and how do I know
והבאת *v'heiveta* refers to the מנחת עומר omer, *minchat omer*? Because it
has the word והבאת *v'heiveta*, והבאתם את עומר ראשית קצירכם אל הכהן
*v'heivetem et omer reishit ktzirchem el hakohen*. Okay, so therefore that's how
he throws in מנחת עומר *minchat omer*. Again nobody's disagreeing להלכה *lohalacha*,
they're learning different things out. והקריבה v'hikriva *V'hikriva*, you shall bring it.
Is again from the פסוק והקריבה הכהן *passuk v'hikriva hakohen*. So that's
the other thing we have to include. לרבות מנחת סוטה להגשה *Lerabot
minchat sota lehagasha*. The מנחת סוטה *minchat sota*. Now how do I
get that out of the word והקריבה *v'hikriva*? וכן הוא אומר והקריב
אותה אל המזבח *V'chen hu omer v'hikriv otah el hamizbe'ach*. You should
bring it to the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. Of course everybody asks if it's
right there in the פסוק והקריב אותה אל המזבח *passuk v'hikriv otah
el hamizbe'ach* why did you need to link it to this to
say הגשה *hagasha*? It's right there that it gets הגשה *hagasha*. So
maybe to tell you where you do the הגשה *hagasha*, which is
more explicit in our פסוק *passuk*. Then it is by the סוטה.
But that's how we know the סוטה gets הגשה. Okay. ודין הוא,
and I could have maybe learned it out logically. ומה מנחת חוטא
שאינה טעונה תנופה טעונה הגשה, umah minchat chotei she-einah teunah tenufah teunah
hagasha, מנחת סוטה שטעונה תנופה אינו דין שטעונה הגשה? minchat sotah she-teunah
tenufah eino din she-teunah hagasha? If a sinner's מנחה you do הגשה,
which we already learned out, certainly a סוטה you should do הגשה
because you also even do תנופה by a סוטה. No, מה למנחת
חוטא שכן באה חטים? mah l'minchat chotei she-kein ba'ah chittim? Maybe מנחת
חוטא is more important, it comes from wheat flour as opposed to
מנחת סוטה that comes from barley flour, so maybe it's not important
to do הגשה. מנחת עומר תוכיח. minchat omer tochiach. How about the
עומר, we just included the עומר, that comes from barley. מה למנחת
עומר שכן טעונה שמן ולבונה? mah l'minchat omer she-kein teunah shemen u'levonah?
That's more important because that gets oil and לבונה. The מנחת סוטה
doesn't get oil and לבונה. מנחת סוטה is like the worst of
all worlds. It's only barley, it's not even wheat, no oil, no
לבונה. So maybe if it's so you know second grade, third grade,
maybe it doesn't get הגשה. And a woman why not?
There you go. You can save all that
for when we learn סוטה. מנחת
חוטא תוכיח. minchat chotei tochiach. So okay, I'll prove it from מנחת
חוטא. That doesn't have oil and לבונה. וחזר הדין. v'chazar hadin. לא
ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה. Each one's distinctive
characteristic is not like the other. הצד השוה שבהן, hatzad hashaweh shebahen,
the common denominator, ששוו בקמיצה, she-shavu b'kmitzah, they get קמיצה,
ושוו להגשה. v'shavu l'hagasha. They get הגשה. אף אני אביא מנחת סוטה
af ani avi minchat sotah ששוו להן לקמיצה תשוו להן להגשה. she-shavatah
lahen l'kmitzah tashveh lahen l'hagasha. I'll include therefore the one of the
סוטה because there's קמיצה, there's also going to be הגשה, so I
don't need a פסוק. No, מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן הוכשרו לבוא
סולת, mah l'hatzad hashaweh shebahen she-kein huchsharu lavo solet, תאמר מנחת סוטה
שהוכשרה לבוא קמח. tomar minchat sotah she-huchshrah lavo kemach.
All of the other ones at least come סולת, solet, which is
fine flour. Again, a distinctive characteristic of the מנחת סוטה is קמח,
kemach, which is more like bran flour, not fine flour. So again,
it has one characteristic which everything else is not like and therefore
maybe you don't do הגשה by מנחת סוטה. As Bobby said, you
know because it's about this woman and sin and so on, it's
really the worst of all מנחות. So maybe it doesn't get the
you know הגשה. תלמוד לומר והקריבה. talmud lomar v'hikriva. Therefore it says
והקריבה to tell you that even that you do. So we'll continue
with this tomorrow but at this stage what we learned is that
basically any מנחה that you do קמיצה for, which you do you
do הגשה. We learn it's in the תורה it's by essentially by
the main מנחות, but from those we've included sinner, עומר, סוטה, all
these things you do קמיצה for. The debate of רבי שמעון and
the חכמים Chachamim is what if you burn it and don't do
קמיצה for? What about מנחת כהנים? minchat kohanim? So that has not
yet been explicitly but you can see the ברייתא braita is following
רבי שמעון because the way the ברייתא articulates the common denominator is
not that some of it is burnt, but that if it has
קמיצה. If it has קמיצה it has הגשה and that's following רבי
שמעון's approach that says you don't do הגשה for מנחת כהנים. minchat
kohanim. Okay, so to be continued tomorrow.